Being not an end-to-end but
作为非端到端
a peer-to-peer technology and
而是点对点的技术
multi conferencing is the
以及主要用例是
main use-case,
多人会议
the perception of the broadcasting industry
人们对围绕WebRTC的广播行业
around WebRTC has never been very good. slide-2
一直不太看好 slide-2
And it has never been seen
它并没有被视作
as a viable
一个可行的
solution for streaming media because it doesn't scale.
流媒体解决方案 因为它不具备扩展性
It is weak on quality at best
它的传输质量难以保证
and it is hard to use. slide-3
而且用起来相当不便 slide-3
The industry is really dominated by video-on-demand models
行业如今实际上由视频点播模式所主导
like Netflix, the Hulu,
如Netflix Hulu Disney+等
or even Disney with does not require real-time. 15-p
甚至不需要实时播放 15-p
However,
然而
the pandemic has really changed all of this
这场疫情确实改变了这一切
and it has accelerated the adoption
它加速了实时媒体
of real-time media workflows
工作流的落地
that have finally bridged the gap between web and broadcast. 20-p
最终弥合了网络和广播之间的差距 20-p
real-time media has enabled a need for interactivity
实时媒体催生了
that requires near zero latency.
对接近零延迟互动的需求
with new use cases that big professional-grade workflows
新的用例使专业级的工作流
possible in consumer grade devices. slide-4
在消费级设备中成为可能 slide-4
WebRTC is the perfect technology for delivering
WebRTC是传递这种实时媒体的
these real-time media. slide-5
理想技术 slide-5
It did what it was designed for in the beginning. slide-6
它做到了面世时的设计初衷 slide-6
And despite some misconceptions,
尽管人们对它有一些误解
it is possible to deliver a high quality media
但通过额外属性 如端到端加密
with broadcast quality at a web scale
或同步广播和SVC支持
with additional properties like end-to-end encryption or simulcast streaming support. slide-7
它仍能在网页上提供广播级高质量媒体 slide-7
However, the lack of a standard signaling protocol
然而 由于缺乏标准的通信协议
has made it impossible for WebRTC to use a wide range of
WebRTC无法使用
tools available and use on a daily basis
流媒体界日常使用的
by the streaming world.
广泛工具
For example, OBS, FFmpeg, or vMix. 36-p
例如OBS FFmpeg和vMix 36-p
Not to mention that the lack of hardware encoders and physical input sources
更不用说它还缺乏许多专业媒体工作流中
that are available here and integrated
广泛可用的硬件编码器和
into many professional media workflows. slide-8
物理输入源 slide-8
In the broadcasting industry, RTMP
在广播行业 RTMP协议
is still ubiquitous for
广泛用于直播流
live streaming and for media ingest, into hundreds or so media platforms. slide-9
和向成百上千的媒体平台上载媒体 slide-9
WebRTC offers a lot of technical advantages
WebRTC在进行实时媒体上载时
when doing live media ingest like with network resiliency
有很多技术优势 如不增加端到端延迟
without increasing
同时提供更好的网络弹性
the end to end delay, by using SVC codec or
通过使用SVC编解码器或同步广播
simulcast where they reuse the server (?) required, with per-codec choices like VP9 or AV1,
复用所需的服务器端处理 选择如VP9或AV1的编解码器
an end to end content as video for content,
端到端的内容如视频内容
but over the delivering network. slide-10
但通过交付网络进行传输 slide-10
When we tried to use WebRTC for media ingest,
当我们尝试使用WebRTC进行媒体上载时
we realized that while WebRTC is the best media transport
我们意识到虽然WebRTC是实时流媒体的
protocol for real time streaming, the lack of a
最佳媒体传输协议 但由于缺乏标准协议
standard protocol has made that each WebRTC streaming
使得每个WebRTC流媒体服务
service requires implementing a custom ad-hoc protocol,
都需要实现一个自定义的临时协议
making it a no-go for hardware encoders and broadcasting tools to adopt it. 55-p
这使得硬件编码器和广播工具无法采用它 55-p
Other media transports could be used for ingest,
其他媒体传输协议可用于上载
but using WebRTC for both ingest and delivery allow to
但使用WebRTC进行上载和传输能够让我们
work natively in browsers avoids protocol translation which
在浏览器中本地运行 避免了由于协议转换
adds delays and implementation complexity.
而增加延迟和实现的复杂性
Avoiding the transcoding by setting
通过设置常见的编解码器
common codecs and use WebRTC features into it. slide-11
以及端到端使用WebRTC功能来避免转码 slide-11
So the solution is simple,
那么解决方案就很简单了
we just need a reference signal protocol.
我们只需要一个参考通讯协议
The requirements for this new protocol would be that it might
对这项新协议的需求是 它能够
be simpler to implement.
更简单地实现
And easy to use at the current RTMP URI, support this
而且在目前的RTMP URI下容易使用
specific ingest use-case
支持特定的上载用例
which is a subset of the WebRTC
这是WebRTC可能用例的
possible use cases because we
一个子集 因为我们
only need support for unidirectional flows.
只需要支持单向流
And we don't need support for re-negotiations. 71-p
而且我们不需要支持再协商 71-p
We need to be fully compliant with WebRTC and RTCWeb specs
我们需要完全符合WebRTC和RTCWeb的规范
but we have to lower
但我们必须降低
their requirements and the complexity
需求和复杂性
to reimplement it so it can be adopted by both
来重新实现它
hardware encoders and brodcasting tools. slide-12
以便它能被硬件编码器和广播工具采用 slide-12
One thing that was clear to us is there was that this new
有一点是清楚的 那就是这个新协议
protocol should reuse
应该尽可能地
the current Web technologies
复用现有的
as much as possible.
Web技术
So we did use HTTP post for exchanging the SDP offer offer and answer.
我们也确实使用了HTTP POST来交换SDP的提议和应答
And the connection state is controlled
而连接状态是由WebRTC的
by the WebRTC ICE states.
ICE和DTLS状态控制的
The authentication is supported by
认证和授权由大多数SDP Rest接口
as most of the SDP rest nowadays does by the
通过HTTP头部Authorization
Authorization HTTP header.
进行支持
The standardization of
此协议的标准制定工作
this protocol is being done at the IETF. slide-13
正由互联网工程任务组牵头推进 slide-13
And there are already some platforms that are implemented
而且已经有一些平台实现了这一协议
like Millicast or media server like Janus
如Millicast 以及Janus之类的媒体服务器
that support it, and we have some client
已经支持这一协议 我们也有一些
implementation based on your GStreamer
基于GStreamer的客户端实现
and of course in JavaScript. 94-p
当然还有基于JavaScript的实现 94-p
The goal is to gain traction so we can get the hardware encoders
我们的目标是能够让硬件编码器实现它
to implement it and be able to use it in the same tools
并能够在同样支持RTMP协议的工具中
that are available for RTMP. slide-14
使用这一协议 slide-14
But this is all that is needed for using WebRTC in a
这就是在专业媒体流中使用WebRTC的
professional media flow? Unfortunately not.
所有需求吗 可惜并非如此
And it is not mainly due to the lack of specifications,
这也并不主要是因为缺乏规范
but mostly because the implementation of many of the
而是因为许多所需功能的实现
features required is lagging behind in most of the browsers,
在大多数浏览器中都是滞后的
and even with (?) API
即使有这样的API来启用这些功能
available to enable them, most of the time, they are in experimental status or hidden
大多数时候 它们都处于实验状态
behind flags, undocumented or difficult to discover. 105-p
隐藏在标记后面 未正式记录或难以发现 105-p
For example, some of
例如 我们在音频方面
the issues that we have found with audio
发现的一些问题
if that WebRTC...
是WebRTC…
we can support multichannel audio with Multiopus.
我们可以用Multiopus支持多声道音频
Multiopus is not official standard
Multiopus并不是官方标准
and it's only supported by Chrome.
它只受Chrome支持
And it is hidden,
而且它是一项隐藏功能
that requests SDP mangling in order to support it. 113-p
需要SDP修改才能支持它 113-p
NetEQ, that is a jitter buffer implementation in all WebRTC browser
NetEQ是一项所有WebRTC浏览器中的抖动缓冲器实现
has issues with music. And for example,
它在音乐方面就存在问题 例如
Lorenzo has made a great presentation on the topic,
Lorenzo就这个话题做了一个很好的演讲
referencing
其中描述了
all the issues that he has found when trying to use WebRTC
他在尝试将WebRTC用于音乐时发现的问题
for music. So I will encourage everyone to watch it. 119-p
所以我建议大家去看一下 119-p
Or for example, the integration between WebRTC and Web Audio
又比如WebRTC和Web Audio之间的整合
has implementation issues on chrome that either adds echo,
在Chrome上存在实现的问题
when you play audio with audio captured by WebRTC
当你用WebRTC播放捕获音频时 会增加回声
and it has been acknowledged by Google itself. 123-p
而且谷歌自己也承认了这一点 123-p
Or for example,
另一个例子是
there is a lack of integration between
WebRTC和WebVTT之间
WebRTC and WebVTT
缺乏整合
making live subtitles impossible. slide-15
使得实时字幕无法实现 slide-15
Also on the video side.
同样在视频方面
For example, SVC extension APIs
例如 SVC扩展API
only working in Chrome and it's an
只能在Chrome中运行
experimental feature,
而且只是一项实验性功能
although this is likely
不过这一情况很可能
going to change in the following weeks. 133-p
在接下来的几周内发生变化 133-p
AV1 is only supported by Chrome and not enabled in it.
AV1编码只受Chrome支持 在Edge中没有启用
Even if they share almost the same codebase.
尽管它们几乎共享相同的代码库 136-p
VP9 profile which supports 10 bits is only supported by Chrome
支持10比特通道的VP9配置文件只受Chrome支持
and only on
而且只支持
the receiving side.
在接收端
And it is experimental in Safari. 140-p
它在Safari中仍处于试验性阶段 140-p
The playoutdelayhint is an optional extension
playoutdelayhint是一个可选的扩展
and it is only supported in chrome. 142-p
它也只受Chrome支持 142-p
Eh,
另一个例子是abs-capture-time
is a header extension that could be used for synchronizing a
它是一个头信息扩展 可用于
video with standard metadata is only supporting in Chrome
同步视频与标准元数据 只受Chrome支持
but it is a thing hidden
但它也是隐藏的
and requires SDP mangling to enable it. 148-p
需要SDP修改来启用它 148-p
And at last, as an example of how professional-grade features
最后再举一个例子 作为专业级功能的
are not always sought to be used with the WebRTC,
视频alpha通道被认为无法用于WebRTC
video alpha is not supported, never meant to be supported in WebRTC
WebRTC也没有预想过支持这一功能
but it is under consideration for being implemented
但在WebCodecs中
in WebCodecs. slide-16
正在考虑实现它 slide-16
So as a conclusion, WebRTC today is (?).
总的来说 现今的WebRTC是可用的
And I will say, even, it is
我想说的是 即使它是
the best option for delivering professional broadcast
以最低延迟传输专业广播质量媒体的最佳选择
quality media with minimal latency,
但为了能够使WebRTC成型
but there is a still a lot of work to do in order to be able
我们仍有很多工作要做
to WHIP WebRTC into shape. slide-17
任重而道远 slide-17
But the good news is that we are on it.
但好消息是 我们已经着手在做了